<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!-- Copyright 2014-2023 Stefan Löffler <st.loeffler@gmail.com> -->
<component type="desktop-application">
	<id>org.tug.texworks.desktop</id>
	<metadata_license>CC0-1.0</metadata_license>
	<project_license>GPL-2.0+</project_license>
	<name>TeXworks</name>
	<name xml:lang="de">TeXworks</name>
	<summary>A simple environment for editing, typesetting, and previewing TeX documents</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="af">'n Eenvoudige omgewing vir redigering, letterset, en vooraflees van TeX dokumente</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="ar">بيئة بسيطة لتحرير وصف ومعاينة مستندات تخ</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="ca">Un entorn senzill per a l'edició, composiciò i vista prèvia de documents TeX</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="cs">Jednoduché prostředí pro úpravu, sazbu a náhled TeXových dokumentů</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="de">Eine einfache Umgebung zum Bearbeiten, Setzen und Darstellen von TeX-Dokumenten</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="es">Un entorno sencillo para editar, compilar y previsualizar documentos TeX</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="fa">محیطی ساده برای ویرایش، حروف‌چینی، و پیش‌نمایش مستندات تک</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="fo">Eitt einfalt umhvørvi til at skriva, seta og lesa TeX-skjøl við</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="fr">Un environnement simple pour éditer, composer et prévisualiser des documents TeX</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="it">Un semplice ambiente per la modifica, la composizione e l'anteprima di documenti TeX</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="ja">TeX文書を作成、タイプセット、プレビューするためのシンプルな統合環境です</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="ko">TeX 문서를 편집, 조판, 미리보기 할 수 있는 심플한 환경</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="nl">Een eenvoudige omgeving voor het aanpassen, typesetten, en vertonen van TeX documenten</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="nn">Eit enkelt miljø for redigering, sideombrekking og vising av TeX-dokument</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="pl">Proste środowisko do edycji, składu oraz przeglądania dokumentów w TeXu</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="pt_BR">TeXworks é um ambiente simples para editar, compilar e prever documentos TeX</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="ru">Простая программа для редактирования, вёрстки и просмотра документов TeX</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="sl">Okolje za enostavno urejanje, stavljenje in predogled TeX-ovih dokumentov</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="tr">TeXworks, TeX belgelerini düzenleme, dizme ve önizleme için basit bir ortamdır</summary>
	<summary xml:lang="zh_CN">一个用于编辑、排版和预览 TeX 文档的简洁集成环境</summary>

	<description>
		<p>
			TeXworks is an environment for authoring TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt, etc) documents, with a
			Unicode-based, TeX-aware editor, integrated PDF viewer, and a clean, simple
			interface accessible to casual and non-technical users.
		</p>
		<p>
			TeXworks is inspired by Dick Koch's award-winning TeXShop program for Mac OS X,
			which has made quality typesetting through TeX accessible to a wider community
			of users, without a technical or intimidating face. The goal of TeXworks is to
			deliver a similarly integrated, easy-to-use environment for users on other
			platforms, especially GNU/Linux and Windows.
		</p>
		<p>
			Among other things, TeXworks features an integrated PDF previewer, synchronization
			between the TeX files and the PDF output, and an extensible scripting interface.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="af">
			TeXworks is 'n omgewing vir die skep van TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt, ens.) dokumente, met 'n
			Unicode-gebaseerde, TeX-bewuste redigeerder, geïntegreerde PDF besigtiger, en 'n skoon,
			eenvoudige koppelvlak wat vir toevallige en nie-tegniese gebruikers toeganklik is.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="af">
			TeXworks is geïnspireer deur Dick Koch se bekroonde TeXShop program vir Mac OS X,
			wat, sonder 'n tegniese of intimiderende voorkoms, kwaliteit lettersetting deur TeX
			toeganklik gemaak het vir 'n wyer gebruikersgemeenskap. Die doel van TeXworks is om 'n
			'n soortgelyk geïntegreerde en vriendelike omgewing te skep vir gebruikers van ander
			platvorms, veral GNU/Linux en Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="af">
			Behalwe ander funksies, vertoon TeXworks 'n geïntegreerde PDF besigtiger, sinkronisasie
			tussen TeX lêers en PDF uitset, en 'n uitbreibare skrip-koppelvlak.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ca">
			TeXworks és un entorn per a l'edició de documents TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt, etc). L'editor
			és compatible amb l'estàndar Unicode, conté un visualitzador de PDF integrat i una interfície
			simple i comprensible per a tot tipus d'usuaris.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ca">
			TeXworks està inspirat en el premiat programa TeXShop per a Mac OS X de Dick Koch, el qual ha
			fet accessible la composició de qualitat a través de TeX a una gran comunitat d'usuaris gràcies a
			eliminar la seva cara tècnica i intimidatòria. L'objectiu de TeXworks és oferir un entorn
			igualment integrat i d'ús senzill per usuaris d'altres plataformes, especialment GNU/Linux i Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ca">
			Entre altres coses, TeXworks presenta un previsualitzador de PDF integrat, sincronització
			entre el fitxer TeX i la sortida PDF, i una interfície d'scripts extensible.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="de">
			TeXworks ist ein Programm, um TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt, etc) Dokumente zu erstellen
			und zu bearbeiten. Es besitzt einen eingebauten Unicode-basierten TeX-Editor,
			eine integrierte PDF Anzeige und eine aufgeräumte, einfach zu verwendende
			Benutzeroberfläche die für gelegentliche und nicht-technische Nutzer leicht
			zu bedienen ist.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="de">
			TeXworks wurde von Dick Kochs preisgekröntem Programm TeXShop für Mac OS X
			inspiriert, das hochqualitativen Schriftsatz mittels TeX ohne einschüchternde
			technische Details einer breiten Nutzerbasis zugänglich gemacht hat. Das Ziel
			von TeXworks ist es, ein gleichermaßen integriertes, einfach zu verwendendes
			Programm auch Nutzern anderer Platformen, insbesondere GNU/Linux und Windows,
			zur Verfügung zu stellen.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="de">
			TeXworks zeichnet sich unter anderem durch eine integrierte PDF Vorschau,
			Synchronisation zwischen TeX- und PDF-Dateien sowie ein erweiterbares
			Skripting-Interface aus.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="es">
			TeXworks es un programa para crear, editar y compilar documentos TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt
			y otros). Dispone de un editor con Unicode incorporado y de un previsualizador PDF
			integrado; cuenta con sincronización entre el archivo TeX y su salida PDF, así como
			una interfaz de scripts extensible.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="es">
			TeXworks se ha inspirado en TeXShop, el afamado programa de Dick Koch para Mac OS X, el cual
			ha facilitado que la composición tipográfica con TeX se haya vuelto accesible para
			una base más grande de usuarios, que no necesariamente cuentan con una amplia formación
			técnica. La meta de TeXworks es ofrecer un entorno igualmente integrado y fácil de usar
			para los usuarios de otros plataformas, especialmente GNU/Linux y Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="es">
			Entre otras cosas, TeXworks cuenta con un visualizador integrado de archivos PDF, es capaz de
			permitir la sincronización entre los archivos TeX y su salida compilada en PDF, y brinda una
			interfaz de scripts que es extensible.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fo">
			TeXworks er eitt umhvørvi til at skriva TeX-skjøl, t.e LaTeX, ConTeXt o.s.fr., við.
			Tað kemur við einum Unicode-grundaðum ritli, sum kennir til TeX, einum innbygdum
			PDF-vísara og einum reinum og einføldum markamóti, sum brúkarar við lítlum tøkniligum 
			innliti kunnu brúka.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fo">
			TeXworks er gjørt við íblástri frá tí virðislønta TeXShop-forritinum, sum Dick Koch
			gjørdi til Mac OS X. TeXShop hevur givið einum størri skara av brúkarum atgongd til
			dygdarseting við TeX uttan at skula møta tøkniligum og ræðandi avbjóðingum. Endamálið
			við TeXworks er at veita eitt líknandi heildarumhvørvi, sum er lætt at brúka hjá brúkarum
			av øðrum skipanum, serliga GNU/Linux og Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fo">
			TeXworks kemur við m.a. einum innbygdum PDF-vísara, synkronisering millum TeX-fílur
			og PDF-úrslitið, umframt eitt skriptmarkamót, ið kann víðkast.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			TeXworks est un environnement de création de documents TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt, etc)
			avec un éditeur Unicode orienté TeX, une visionneuse PDF intégrée et une interface
			claire et simple, accessible à l'utilisateur occasionnel ou sans bagage technique.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			TeXworks est inspiré du programme primé de Dick Koch TeXShop pour le Mac OS X,
			qui a rendu la composition typographique de qualité accessible par TeX à une
			large communauté d’utilisateurs, sans aspect technique ou intimidant. Le but
			de TeXworks est de fournir de la même façon un environnement intégré et facile
			d’utilisation pour des utilisateurs sur d’autres plateformes, en particulier
			sous GNU/Linux et Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="fr">
			Parmi d’autres choses, TeXworks inclut une visionneuse PDF intégrée, la
			synchronisation entre les fichiers TeX et la sortie PDF, et une interface de
			scripts extensible.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="it">
			TeXworks è un ambiente completo per la creazione, la gestione e la manipolazione di
			di documenti basati su TeX e derivati (LaTex, ConTeXt, etc). E'  dotato di un proprio
			editor compatibile con lo standard Unicode, di un visualizzatore di PDF integrato e di
			una interfaccia semplice e comprensibile, accessibile a ogni tipologia di utente.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="it">
			TeXworks è ispirato a TeXShop, il celebrato programma di Dick Koch per Mac OS X, che ha
			consentito a una vasta comunità di utenti di cimentarsi con la qualità di composizione
			tipografica offerta da TeX senza farsi impressionare dai suoi aspetti più ostici.
			Lo scopo di TeXworks è offrire agli utenti di altri sistemi operativi, GNU/Linux e
			Windows in primis, lo stesso tipo di approccioi amichevole.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="it">
			Tra le caratteristiche principali di TeXworks spiccano il visualizzatore integrato di file PDF,
			la sincronizzazone tra file di TeX e il PDF generato e un linguaggio di scripting estensibile.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ja">
			TeXworksは、TeX文書 (LaTeX, ConTeXtなど) を作成するための統合環境です。Unicodeを標準として、
			TeX文書の作成支援機能を持ったエディター、組み込みのPDFビューアーを備え、ITに詳しくないユーザーでも簡単に
			使用できるシンプルなユーザーインターフェースを提供します。
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ja">
			TeXworksは、Dick KochによるMac OS用の優れたプログラムTeXShopに触発されて開発されました。
			TeXShopは、幅広い層のユーザーに、裏側の技術的な要素を意識せずに利用できる、
			TeXによる高品質な組版環境を提供しています。TeXworksが目指すゴールは、TeXShopと同様の統合された組版環境を、GNU/LinuxやWindowsをはじめとした
			Mac OS以外のプラットフォームにも提供することです。
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ja">
			TeXworksの特徴として、組み込みのPDFビューアー、TeXファイルとPDF出力の間の同期、スクリプトによる機能拡張などがあります。
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ko">
			TeXworks는 TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt 등) 문서를 작성하기 위한 환경입니다. 유니코드 기반의
			텍 친화적인 에디터, 내장 PDF 뷰어, 깔끔하고 단순한 인터페이스를 가지고 있어
			초보 사용자들도 쉽게 사용할 수 있습니다.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ko">
			TeXworks는 Dick Koch의 Mac OS X 용 프로그램 TeXShop에서 영향을 받았습니다.
			수상경력에 빛나는 이 프로그램은 접근 곤란한 전문적 기술적 외양을 걷어내어 
			텍을 이용한 고품질 조판을 폭넓은 사용자층에 보급하였습니다. TeXworks의 목표는
			이와 같이 사용하기 쉬운 통합적인 환경을 GNU/Linux나 Windows 등 다른 플랫폼
			사용자들에게도 제공하는 것입니다.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ko">
			무엇보다 TeXworks는 PDF 미리보기 기능 내장, 텍 파일과 PDF 결과물 간 연동,
			확장가능한 스크립트 활용 인터페이스 등의 특징을 가지고 있습니다.  
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="nl">
			TeXworks ist een omgeving om documenten voor TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt, enzovoort)
			op te stellen en te bewerken. Het bevat een op Unicode gebaseerde TeX-editor,
			een geïntegreerde PDF-viewer en een eenvoudige, opgeruimde interface die ook
			voor incidentele gebruikers en niet-professionals gemakkelijk te gebruiken is.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="nl">
			Het ontwerp van TeXworks is geïnspireerd op het gelauwerde programma TeXShop
			dat door Dick Koch is gemaakt voor Mac OS X en dat kwaliteitszetwerk mogelijk
			heeft gemaakt voor een grote gemeenschap van gebruikers, zonder technisch of
			intimiderend over te komen. Het doel van TeXworks is om net zo'n geïntegreerde
			en gemakkelijk te gebruiken omgeving te bieden voor gebruikers van andere
			besturingssystemen, in het bijzonder GNU/Linux en Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="nl">
			TeXworks munt onder andere uit door een geïntegreerde PDF-viewer, synchronisatie
			tussen de TeX-bestanden en het resultaat in PDF-formaat, en een functionaliteit
			die is uit te breiden door middel van scripts.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="nn">
			TeXworks er eit miljø for redigering av TeX-dokument (LaTeX, ConTeXt, …),
			med eit Unicode-basert skriveprogram, integrert PDF-visar og eit oversiktleg
			brukargrensesnitt, som høver for vanlege, ikkje-tekniske brukarar.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="nn">
			TeXworks er inspirert av Dick Koch sitt prisvinnande og brukarvennlege program TeXShop
			for Mac OS X, som har gjort typografisk avansert sideombrekking via TeX tilgjengeleg for
			eit større publikum. Målet med TeXworks er eit liknande integrert skrivemiljø for
			brukarar på andre plattformer, spesielt GNU/Linux og Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="nn">
			TeXworks støttar blant anna innebygd PDF-vising, synkronisering mellom TeX-filer
			og PDF-resultat og moglegheit for utvidingar via eit eige skriptgrensesnitt.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="pl">
			TeXworks to środowisko do tworzenia dokumentów opartych na TeXu (LaTeX, ConTeXt,
			itp) wyposażone w edytor zgodny z TeXem, używający kodowania Unicode,
			zintegrowany z przeglądarką PDF, z prostym i jasnym interfejsem przyjaznym
			zwłaszcza dla  przypadkowych i nie-technicznych użytkowników.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="pl">
			TeXworks jest inspirowany wielokrotnie nagradzanym programem TeXShop Dicka Kocha
			dla systemu Mac OS X, który sprawił, że wysokiej jakości skład tekstów z
			wykorzystaniem TeXa stał się dostępny dla szerszej społeczności użytkowników,
			bez technicznego doświadczenia.. Celem TeXworks jest dostarczenie podobnie
			zintegrowanego, łatwego w użyciu środowiska dla użytkowników na innych
			platformach, zwłaszcza GNU/Linux i Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="pl">
			TeXworks oferuje, między innymi, zintegrowany podgląd PDF, synchronizację między
			plikami TeX a wyjściem PDF oraz rozszerzalny interfejs skryptów.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ru">
			TeXworks — это среда для подготовки документов в TeX (LaTeX, ConTeXt и др.) формате,
			состоящая из редактора, поддерживающего Unicode и встроенного просмотра PDF документов
			соединённые в простом и понятном интерфейсе.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ru">
			На создание TeXworks сподвигла популярная на Mac OS X программа TeXShop, созданная
			Диком Кохом, позволившая большому числу пользователей без лишних усилий получать
			высококлассные документы используя TeX. Цель TeXworks — предоставить те же
			возможности интегрированного и простого в использовании окружения для пользователей
			других платформ, в особенности GNU/Linux и Windows.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="ru">
			Среди прочего в TeXworks есть встроенный просмотр PDF, синхронизация между исходными
			TeX файлами и PDF выводом, и возможности расширения функциональности с помощью сценариев.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="sl">
			TeXworks je program za pripravo TeX-ovih dokumentov (vključno z LaTeX-om, ConTeXt-om, itd.).
			Vključuje urejevalnik besedila (s podporo Unicode-u in barvanju TeX-ove sintakse)
			ter integriran pregledovalnik PDF-jev. Ponuja preprost uporabniški vmesnik,
			primeren tudi za manj tehnično podkovane uporabnike.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="sl">
			Inspiracija za program izhaja iz programa TeXShop za macOS, za katerega je
			avtor Dick Koch prejel posebno nagrado, in ki je približal kvalitetno stavljenje
			besedil širši množici uporabnikov, brez nepotrebne tehnične navlake.
			Misija TeXworksa je uporabnikom ostalih operacijskih sistemov – še zlasti
			Linuxašem in uporabnikom Oken – približati podobno uporabniško izkušnjo.
		</p>
		<p xml:lang="sl">
			TeXworks med ostalim ponuja vgrajen pregledovalnik PDF-jev, sinhronizacijo med
			izvorno kodo in PDF-jem ter razširljivost s skriptami.
		</p>
	</description>

	<categories>
		<category>Office</category>
		<category>Publishing</category>
		<category>TextEditor</category>
		<category>Viewer</category>
		<category>Qt</category>
	</categories>

	<screenshots>
		<screenshot type="default">
			<image width="1280" height="800">https://www.tug.org/texworks/img/texworks-linux.png</image>
			<caption>The TeXworks source and preview windows</caption>
		</screenshot>
	</screenshots>
	<url type="homepage">https://www.tug.org/texworks/</url>
	<url type="help">https://github.com/TeXworks/manual</url>
	<url type="bugtracker">https://github.com/TeXworks/texworks/issues</url>
	<url type="translate">https://github.com/TeXworks/texworks/wiki/Translating</url>
	<update_contact>texworks@tug.org</update_contact>

	<provides>
		<binary>texworks</binary>
	</provides>
	<launchable type="desktop-id">texworks.desktop</launchable>
	<content_rating type="oars-1.0" />

	<releases>
		<release version="0.6.8" date="2023-02-18" />
		<release version="0.6.7" date="2022-02-26" />
		<release version="0.6.6" date="2021-03-11" />
		<release version="0.6.5" date="2020-03-25" />
		<release version="0.6.4" date="2020-03-15" />
		<release version="0.6.3" date="2019-03-16" />
		<release version="0.6.2" date="2017-04-30" />
		<release version="0.6.1" date="2016-05-01" />
		<release version="0.6.0" date="2016-04-03" />
		<release version="0.4.6" date="2015-04-03" />
		<release version="0.4.5" date="2015-03-15" />
		<release version="0.4.4" date="2012-04-29" />
		<release version="0.4.3" date="2011-06-29" />
		<release version="0.4.2" date="2011-06-26" />
		<release version="0.4.1" date="2012-05-27" />
		<release version="0.4.0" date="2012-05-21" />
		<release version="0.2.3" date="2009-10-12" />
		<release version="0.2.2" date="2009-10-10" />
		<release version="0.2.1" date="2009-10-10" />
		<release version="0.2.0" date="2009-09-30" />
	</releases>
</component>

